Guide to the Yale Tocqueville Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- TOCQUEVILLE & BEAUMONT, AFTER 1840; D.
  - Beaumont Life and Career, 1840-1866; 4
    - r. Letters by Gustave de Beaumont (Box 53)
      -du port de Stora, 30 mai 1841, from his African trip with Tocqueville (Larminat to GWP)
      -"a bord du bateau a vapeur le Tartare," 9 juin 1841, on Tocqueville's illness and their return (Larminat to GWP)
      -Tocqueville, mercredi matin, 22 7bre, about a happy visit to Tocqueville with expedition to Cherbourg, and reading by Ampere from his book about America (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, dimanche matin, 26 avril [presumably 1857] (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, jeudi 9 h. du soir, 23 rue de Miromesnil, from Edmond de Lafayette's office (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, mercredi matin (no year) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, rue and hotel Miromesnil, vendredi, 22 ma, Paris, vendredi matin, 23 juillet, 6 h. du matin, postscript from Ste. Barbe, 10 h. 1/2 (Larminat to GWP)
      -dimanche matin, 7 h., 26 7bre 1857 (on blue paper) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, lundi matin, 17 janvier 41 rue and hotel Miromesnil (8 pages) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, dimanche, 25 avril 1858 (Larminat to GWP)
      -Beaumont-la-Chartre, dimanche matin, 9 mai 1858 (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, hotel Miromesnil, lundi matin, 15 9bre 1858 (blue paper) (Larminat to GWP)
      -21 decembre 1858 (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, 19 janvier 1859, mercredi, rue and hotel Miromesnil (6 pages) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, 21 janvier 1859, rue and hotel Miromesnil, vendredi (6 pages) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, dimanche matin, 23 janvier 1859 (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, lundi matin, 24 janvier (1859 written in pencil, presumably by Redier) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, vendredi, 11 mars (1859 in pencil [by Redier?]) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, samedi, 12 mars 1859 (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, dimanche, 13 mars 1859 (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, 14 mars 1859, lundi (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, 15 mars 1859 (mardi in pencil), (with added note) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, 16 mars 1859 (mercredi in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -mercredi matin, 16 mars (1859 in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, 17 mars 1859 (jeudi in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, samedi, 19 mars 1859 (samedi in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, 21 mars 1859 (lundi in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, 22 mars 1859 mardi (mardi in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, 23 mars 1859 (mercredi in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, 24 mars (jeudi in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, 25 mars 1859, 8 h. 1/2 (vendredi in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes 26 mars 1859 (samedi in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -dimanche, 27 mars 1859 (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, lundi, 28 mars 1859 (lundi in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, mardi, 29 mars 1859 (mardi in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, 30 mars 1859 (mercredi in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, 31 mars 1859 (jeudi in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, 1er avril 1859, vendredi (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, 2 avril 1859 (samedi in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, 3 avril 1859 (dimanche in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, 4 avril 1859 (lundi in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Cannes, 4 avril au soir (1859 lundi in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, jeudi matin (7 avril 1859 [?] in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -samedi matin, 9 h. (jour de la mort de Tocqueville, 16 avril 1859, in pencil), (with added sheet in same hand identifying Tocqueville's death date as 16 avril 1859) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, 41 rue de Miromesnil, dimanche matin, 17 avril (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, lundi, 18 avril, small note (Larminat to GWP)
      -samedi matin (23 avril 59, in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, dimanche, 24 avril 1859 (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, lundi, 25 avril 1859 (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, mardi matin, rue and hotel Miromesnil 41 (26 avril 1859, in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, mercredi, 27 avril 1859 (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, jeudi, 28 avril 1859 (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, 29 avril, vendredi matin (1859 in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, samedi matin, 30 avril (1859 in pencil and postmark) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, dimanche matin (30 avril 1859, in pencil, with mai postmarks) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, lundi matin (1er mai 1859, in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, mardi matin (2 mai 1859, in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, mercredi matin (3 mai 1859, in pencil) (Larminat to GWP)
      -dimanche matin, 19 juin 1859 (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, samedi matin, 21 janvier 1860 (on blue paper) (Larminat to GWP)
      -dimanche matin 22 janvier 1860, Paris (blue paper) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Tocqueville, mardi, 24 janvier 60 (Larminat to GWP)
      -Tocqueville, jeudi matin, 26 janvier 1860 (Larminat to GWP)
      -Beaumont-la-Chartre, mercredi matin, 22 f[evri]er (Larminat to GWP)
      -Beaumont-la-Chartre, vendredi matin, 24 fevrier (Larminat to GWP)
      -Beaumont-la-Chartre, samedi matin (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, mercredi matin (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, 29 mai, mardi, rue and hotel Miromesnil 41 (Larminat to GWP)
      -vendredi matin, 1er juin 1860 (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, jeudi matin, 23 aout (1860 postmark) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, lundi matin (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, lundi soir (postmarked 3 septembre 1860) (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, mardi matin (postmarked 4 septembre 1860) (Larminat to GWP)
      -41 rue and hotel Miromesnil, 8 decembre, samedi (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, lundi, 10 decembre 1860 (Larminat to GWP)
      -Paris, mardi, 11 Xbre 1860, short note (Larminat to GWP)
      -Valognes, 24 Xbre, samedi (must be 1864), after Mary de Tocqueville's death (Larminat to GWP)
  - Unpublished Manuscripts on Tocqueville or Beaumont, 5
    - a. Bergamo. Carbon typescript of an M.A. thesis based in part on the Yale Tocqueville Manuscripts (now missing). 1974 (Box 53)
    - b. Benedict Songy, O.S.B. Tocqueville and Slavery. Microfilm of a dissertation based in part on the Yale Tocqueville Manuscripts. (Box 54)
    - c. James T. Schleifer, "The Making of Tocqueville's Democratie ", Yale Ph.D., 1972, University of Michigan Microfilms. [This missing as of 4/1/82.] (Box 54)
    - d. Alvis Lee Tinnin, "Gustave de Beaumont: Prophet of the American Dilemma", Yale Ph.D. 1961. [missing?] (Box 54)
  - Tocqueville Exhibitions and Celebrations, 6
    - a. La commission nationale pour la publication des oeuvres completes d'Alexis de Tocqueville organise... un colloque... 5-8 novembre 1959. (Box 54)
    - b. Bibliotheque Nationale. Hommage a Alexis de Tocqueville (1805-1859). Manuscrits - Portraits - Souvenirs. (Box 54)
    - c. Beinecke Library. Exhibition: Images of America after the Revolution. Alexis de Tocqueville and Gustave de Beaumont Visit the Early Republic. April 6 - June 23, 1976. Lecture by George W. Pierson, 'Tocqueville's Visions of Democracy' (Yale Law School Auditorium, 7 April 1976) published in the Yale University Library Gazette for July 1976, p. 1-17. (Box 54)
- MISCELLANEOUS, E.
  - Paul Lambert White and his Tocqueville papers, 1
    - 1. a. Letter from Mrs. Paul L. White giving White papers to the Paul L. White Memorial Foundation (which is to turn them over to Sterling Memorial Library, 1938). (Box 55)
      - b. Memo of J.M.S. Allison. (Box 55)
    - 2. White: Notes and Papers.
      These notes and documents will repay study by further Tocqueville scholars, for White's intuitions, and for his references to and quotations from documents, some of which have since been mislaid or lost.
      - a. Tocqueville writing: 2 bibliographies in White's own hand. (Copied in E.IV.b., d.) (Box 55)
      - b. Notes on Tocqueville Education, Character, etc. - still useful for comments by Senior and other writers on Tocqueville (Box 55)
      - c. Notes on Democratie and on Tocqueville manuscript - with some White ideas: still worth consulting. (Box 55)
      - d. Notes on Tocqueville later life and character, from O.C. and few writers - still useful (Box 55)
      - e. Notes on U.S. and American trip from O.C. and Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS. - three bundles of notes: - nothing new. (Box 55)
      - f. Notes on Tocqueville Ideas, Methods, Character: from O.C., Yale Tocqueville MSS, etc. three bundles of notes: nothing new. (Box 55)
      - g. Identification of Tocqueville's American Acquaintances: (copied in E.IV.b.) (Box 55)
      - h. Odd notes. (Box 55)
    - 3. White drafts for Essay and Book.
      - a. Tentative table of contents. (Box 56)
      - b. Introduction or Opening Chapter [?]: 2 drafts. (Box 56)
      - c. Chapter one: draft. (Box 56)
      - d. Draft for article in The Yale Review [?] (Box 56)
      - e. White Graduate School Report on Franco-American relations, 1834-1835. (Box 56)
  - G. W. Pierson - French Correspondence, 2
    For these letters, see GWP.
    - a. Letters to, and from, Tocquevilles, Beaumonts, Stoffels, Romanets, Redier, Doysie, Bonnel, etc., etc., including Paul White correspondence with same: 1920-1938. (Box 57)
    - b. Correspondence with Tocqueville and Beaumont families, J.P. Mayer, and other European scholars. (Box 57)
  - G. W. Pierson - American Correspondence, 3
    - a. Two letter files, containing letters to and from scholars, librarians, descendants of Tocqueville's American acquaintances, prison experts, officials, etc., etc.: 1930-1938. (Box 58)
    - a. Two letter files, containing letters to and from scholars, librarians, descendants of Tocqueville's American acquaintances, prison experts, officials, etc., etc.: 1930-1938. (Box 59)
    - b. GWP correspondence with American scholars and others since 1938. (Box 83)
    - b. GWP correspondence with American scholars and others since 1938. (Box 84)
    - c. GWP files of Tocqueville clippings, articles, speeches, etc. (Box 83)
    - c. GWP files of Tocqueville clippings, articles, speeches, etc. (Box 84)
  - G. W. Pierson - Notes and Catalogues, 4
    - a. Notes on Tocqueville and Beaumont - youth and American trip: 1802-1832. (Box 60)
      A 5 x 8 file box of notes from manuscripts and secondary sources, compiled for the writing of T. and B. in America. These notes were quite largely used and contain little now unexplored material. They are still useful for reconstructing the American experiences.
    - b. Notes on Tocqueville and Beaumont, 1832-1866. (Box 61)
      Second 5 x 8 file box of notes gathered from T. and B. in America contains:
      (1) Material for writing of their books, 1832-1840.
      (2) A few new and still unexplored materials from White and GWP.
      (3) Bibliographical materials on Tocqueville and Beaumont
    - c. GWP Book Manuscripts. (For all these materials, except 5 and 6, see GWP.)
      - 1. Rough drafts and Manuscript for GWP thesis: "Two Frenchmen in America" 1933. (Box 62)
      - 2. Rough drafts, Ms., galley and page proofs for T. and B. in America - 1938. (Box 63)
      - 2. Rough drafts, Ms., galley and page proofs for T. and B. in America - 1938. (Box 64)
      - 2. Rough drafts, Ms., galley and page proofs for T. and B. in America - 1938. (Box 65)
      - 2. Rough drafts, Ms., galley and page proofs for T. and B. in America - 1938. (Box 66)
      - 2. Rough drafts, Ms., galley and page proofs for T. and B. in America - 1938. (Box 67)
      - 3. Typed Ms. of T. and B. in America, carbon copy. (Box 68)
      - 3. Typed Ms. of T. and B. in America, carbon copy. (Box 69)
      - 4. Typed Ms. of T. and B. in America, (as it was before cutting - summer of 1937). (Box 70)
      - 4. Typed Ms. of T. and B. in America, (as it was before cutting - summer of 1937). (Box 71)
      - 5. Illustration cuts used in Book. These cuts now in Yale Tocqueville MSS. (See also B.III.c) (Box 72)
      - 5. Illustration cuts used in Book. These cuts now in Yale Tocqueville MSS. (See also B.III.c) (Box 73)
      - 5. Illustration cuts used in Book. These cuts now in Yale Tocqueville MSS. (See also B.III.c) (Box 74)
      - 5. Illustration cuts used in Book. These cuts now in Yale Tocqueville MSS. (See also B.III.c) (Box 75)
      - 6. Roll "R" - a long outline of all the materials on their American trip: constructed by GWP so as to show the character of the Yale Tocqueville Manuscripts as of 1930. To distinguish a particular diary note - when T. and B. in America gives only a general reference to "Tocqueville diary" - consult the Roll at the date of the given conversation: the diary will be identified. This Roll is now in the Yale Tocqueville Manuscripts. (Box 76 (Oversize))
      - 7. GWP miscellaneous notes and manuscripts (no longer of much value) (Box 77)
      - 8. GWP - special records connected with publications of T. and B. in America. (Box 78 (Oversize))
    - d. GWP box of bibliographical notes and lists of reviews. (Box 79)
    - E.IV.e. CATALOGUES AND INVENTORIES OF TOCQUEVILLE MANUSCRIPT COLLECTIONS.
      Altogether we know of seven catalogues or inventories of Tocqueville manuscripts. Originally Paul L. White made three [1W] [2W] [3W]. Then GWP inventoried what in 1930 he found at Tocqueville [T], and what by 1938 had been collected at Yale [Y]. In the late 1930's someone reclassified the manuscripts at Tocqueville [XT]. Finally in 1955-56 Andre Jardin made his own inventory of what had been turned over by Comte Jean de Tocqueville to the editors of the new "definitive" edition at the Bibliotheque de l'Institut.
      - E.IV.e.1. [1W] (First?) (Box 80)
        Catalogue made by Paul Lambert White in 1919 or 1920 (with typed copy by GWP in 1959). No title. In 21 manuscript pages. Lists 19 bundles or packages of Tocqueville's American Manuscripts, which I believe White found at the Tocqueville Chateau in Normandy (see description of package 15 by White). GWP saw most of the originals there in 1929-31. Copies, made for White and for GWP by Bonnel, are now at Yale. See [Y] below. But some of the originals have been mislaid or have disappeared.
      - E.IV.e.2. [2W] (Second?) (Box 80)
        Catalogue made by White in 1919 or 1920 (with typed copy by GWP in 1938). No title. In 62 pages. Lists 7 great packages, each package containing many dossiers. This appears to be the inventory of all the Tocqueville and related manuscripts which White found with Antoine Redier, who was working on a biography of Tocqueville. A huge collection. Out of it White apparently took certain American materials (see [3W] below) for reproduction by Abel Doysie's copyists. The rest were apparently never copied for White or for Yale. A certain number got back to the Tocqueville Chateau, and are now available (see Jardin's notes for GWP typed copy), but the greater part have simply disappeared.
      - E.IV.e.3. [3W] (Third?) (Box 80)
        Catalogue made by White, in 1919 or 1920 (with typed copy by GWP in 1959). No title. In 20 pages. Lists 5 dossiers (changed from an original 3). Analyzes the American materials, apparently found with Redier (see [2W] above) and set aside for copying by Doysie's copyists. Scrap of paper gives the instructions for copying. Many of the copies are now at Yale, but some important files never got to Yale. Very few of the originals seem ever to have got back to Tocqueville, and almost all of them were missing in 1956-57.
      - E.IV.e.4. [T] Inventaire des documents d'Alexis de Tocqueville by GWP. (Box 80)
        Tocqueville Tocqueville MSS: brief classification of the Tocqueville manuscript archive at the Tocqueville Chateau, as found and reorganized by GWP in 1930. The ribbon copy of this Inventaire was given to Comte Jean de Tocqueville; a carbon copy is at Yale. All the manuscripts here listed ought still to be in existence, though the Jardin Inventory [J] shows that certain manuscripts have either been set aside or mislaid or lost, while some additional manuscripts have been found. The Yale copy of [T] is annotated to show the differences noted between [T] and [J] by Jardin in 1956.
      - E.IV.e.5. [XT] (Box 80)
        Inventory or new classification made at Tocqueville by M. [?] in 193[?]. GWP has never seen a copy. Presumably in hands of Comte de Tocqueville.
      - E.IV.e.6. [J] (Box 80)
        Inventaire made by M. Andre Jardin in the years 1955?-56 of all the Tocqueville manuscripts, as confided to the care of the Commission Nationale pour la publication des Oeuvres d'Alexis de Tocqueville, and deposited in the Bibliotheque de l'Institut. This inventory shows that certain manuscripts have been withheld, or mislaid or lost, since [T] was made. Also many manuscripts from [2W] apparently never got back into the Tocqueville archives. Use restricted.
      - E.IV.e.7. [Y] Catalogue of Tocqueville-Beaumont Archive at Yale. (Box 81)
        Originally constructed by GWP in 1938, in two copies of 41 pages. In 1959 revised and enlarged to include important acquisitions of recent years. In 1964 again enlarged and retyped. Shows what original manuscripts, what copies, and whate notes had been accumulated at the Yale Library or in the personal possession of GWP. Identifies the source of each document or photo or copy.
      - E.IV.e.8. [8] The lost Tocqueville manuscripts (all in our GWP files) (Box 81)
        a. List of lost Tocqueville American manuscripts
        b. List of lost Tocqueville manuscripts of all kinds.
        c. Correspondence on lost Tocqueville and Beaumont manuscripts
        d. Some possibilities (1959)
        Note: A number of the copies of Tocqueville and Beaumont manuscripts, made by Doysie about 1920-1921, or by Bonnel later, now have a superior value, since the originals have apparently disappeared (see repeated comments above).
        In the summer of 1959, GWP had White's catalogues 1W and 3W copied by typewriter in such a form as to make it easier to identify each document and to find its present location or the location of some copy. In the year 1955-56, GWP consulted Andre Jardin who was secretary for the committee publishing the new definitive edition of the Works of Alexis de Tocqueville. Jardin compared his own inventory [J], with catalogues [T], [1W], [2W], and [3W], and made some notes to indicate what he thought was missing from his own collections. These will be found in the appropriate folders, E.IV.e. 1, 2, 3, 4.
        E.IV.e.4. then becomes key: Inventaire des Documents d'Alexis de Tocqueville, with notes by GWP and Andre Jardin to indicate what was missing in Paris in 1956, and what may either have been lost or withheld by Comte de Tocqueville from the archives at the Bibliotheque de l'Institut.
  - G. W. Pierson - Further information for the use of the Tocqueville MSS, 5
    Before anyone does extensive work with these papers, he or she should be familiar with certain facts in their history.
    - E.V.a. The Beaumont Connections: (Box 81)
      When Alexis de Tocqueville died in 1859, he left all his papers with his wife, Mary Mottley. This Englishwoman, who was not popular with Tocqueville's brothers and their families, first authorized Gustave de Beaumont to publish many of Tocqueville's papers in the Oeuvres Completes, which Beaumont proceeded to edit. Then, on her death in 1865, she left all of Tocqueville's manuscripts to Gustave de Beaumont: i.e. outside the family.
      The Tocquevilles were outraged at such a breach of family usage, and no better pleased to have the publication and royalty rights (including the title to the as yet unpublished "Souvenirs") falling to Beaumont's son, Antonin. In 1891, therefore, in consideration of a certain sum of money, Comte Christian de Tocqueville secured title and possession again for his family. Unfortunately, the heirs of the two principals to this bargain were long inclined to believe that perfect faith had not or might not have been kept - the Tocquevilles suspecting that not all of the papers were delivered, the Beaumonts nursing a vague feeling that they might have been done out of something.
      To settle the thing in my own mind, I went over the Beaumont-la-Chartre and the Tocqueville Chateau papers very carefully, compared my findings with the bill of sale, and was soon thoroughly persuaded that good faith had been kept. The bill of sale seemed to cover substantially all of the Tocqueville papers that the Beaumonts had possessed, except Tocqueville's letters to Beaumont which belonged to the Beaumont family, and except for Tocqueville's notes on their prison book on which Beaumont had done most of the work. I told both of the families that things seemed to have been handled with honor and they professed to believe me; however, such legends die hard. In any case, to work with the papers of two mutually suspicious families was, and perhaps will remain, a delicate matter.
    - E.V.b. Certain of the Tocqueville and certain of the Beaumont papers have disappeared. (Box 81)
      (See above, E.IV.e.)
      When White visited France in 1920-1921, he found the Tocqueville manuscripts above referred to partly in the Tocqueville Chateau and partly in the Paris office of Antoine Redier, who was then engaged in writing his Comme disait Monsieur de Tocqueville... (1926). These last papers have never been fully returned to the Tocqueville Chateau, though Redier told me in 1931 that he no longer had them but had returned them to the Tocqueville family. One possible explanation is that Redier managed to mislay some of them. I saw him and got the impression that he had too many irons in the fire and had a terrible memory. I talked with him several times and, the last time in 1931, he still had some Beaumont family papers which I returned to the Beaumonts for him, with apologies for his oversight. Another clue may be that Redier loaned some Tocqueville manuscripts to Roland-Marcel, who was doing a thesis on Tocqueville, and Roland-Marcel may not have returned them. It is possible again that the young Tocquevilles after the death of Comte Christian, their father (it was he that made the arrangements with Redier and with White), may have mislaid the papers returned by Redier. In this case, the lost manuscript should be at 4 rue de Chanaleilles, Paris 7e, which I have never had the chance to search. In any case, I am certain that some of the Redier Tocqueville manuscripts were not at Tocqueville in 1929-1931, and had dropped out of sight since 1921; while still others which I saw at Tocqueville have not been turned over to the editors at the Institut.
    - E.V.c. (Box 81)
      A scholar working in the Yale Tocqueville MSS. should realize that by far the greatest archive is that now in the hands of the committee which is editing the so-called Definitive Edition of the works of Alexis de Tocqueville, under a national commission, supported by the French government and indirectly drawing on some support from the Rockefeller Foundation. The editors have accumulated the Tocqueville papers at the library of the Institut and have been publishing under the directorship of J. Peter Mayer and an editorial committee headed by Charles Pouthas, with Andre Jardin as Secretaire. J. Peter Mayer got microfilms or transcripts of certain of the missing documents from copies of same in the Yale Tocqueville Manuscripts. He has then published the Tocqueville American Diaries in French and presently in an English edition. The Yale documents, therefore, should always be checked against the published volumes. The same is true, or will be true, of the Tocqueville - Beaumont Correspondence which Charles Pouthas and others have been editing.
      Unfortunately, during the process of getting out this edition, the papers have not been available to scholars.